A Guide to the Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse, 1985-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse 1985-1994
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10726-l,-m
This collection consists of ca. 1,060 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2.5 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Alan Cheuse of Fairfax, Virginia, placed his papers on loan to the Library on September 17, 1993, and on May 3, 1994. The papers were purchased by the Library on September 11, 2003.
Scope and Content Information
These additions to the papers of Alan Cheuse, American novelist and reviewer, ca. 1,060 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2.5 linear shelf feet), ca. 1985-1994, consist of his personal and professional correspondence, book reviews by or about Cheuse, appointment calendars, printed material, manuscripts of short stories and articles by Cheuse and other writers, a promotional poster from Grove Press, cassette tape recordings of talks and readings by Cheuse, The Sound of Writing typescripts and production schedules for National Public Radio, and interviews with Cheuse, one a videocassette recording interview with WMU - TV in Marquette, Michigan.
Correspondents and topics in the general correspondence (Boxes 4-6) include: Lee Abbott, (1992 Nov 16; 1993 Feb 6); Joyce Adler, (1992 Apr 19); John W. Aldridge, (1993 Nov 2, 8, 22); Barbara Ascher (1992 Sep 30; 1993 Apr 19); Anselm Atkins, (1992 Nov 7); Lynne Barrett, (1994 Mar 20); Richard Bass, (1992 May 6, Jun 18; 1993 Dec 5); Rex Batson, (1992 May 13); Steve Becker, (1992 Jul 13, Nov 7); Elizabeth Benedict, (1993 Jan 21); Sara Bettencourt, (1992 Jun 26); Staige D. Blackford, (1993 May 7; 1994 Apr 13); James D. Bloom, (1992 Jul 1, 22, Dec 3; 1993 Oct 27, Nov 11, Dec 27); Linda Burgess, (1993 Jun 7); Steve Chapman, (1992 Aug 6); Duncan Christy, (1992 Mar 23, Jun 24; 1993 Apr 27); Daisy Chun-Rhodes, (1993 Apr 2); Edward M. Cifelli, (1990 Jun 20); Evan Connell, (1993 Oct 13); Lee Cullum, (1992 Jun 11, Sep 22); Deborah Cummins, (1992 Aug 19; Oct 5); Richard Currey, (1992 Nov 21; 1993 Jan 19); C. Michael Curtis, (1993 Mar 17); Dalkey Archive Press (1989 Feb 10, with Cheuse comments re book reviewing); Liz Darhansoff, (1993 Feb 1); Davenport Productions (1989 Mar 20); Nicholas Delbanco, (1992 Jul 30, Sep 27, Oct 31, Dec 4, 30; 1993 Jan 15, Apr 1, May 11, 29, Jul 12, Oct 4, 10; 1994 Apr 23); Janice F. Delaney, (1993 May 20; 1994 May 25); E.L. Doctorow, (1993 Aug 13); Carolyn Doty, (1992 Aug 17); Rita Dove, (1989 Jun 1; 1993 Jan 5); Robert Drake, (1992 Oct 13); Jack Driscoll, (1992 Nov 10); Robert Dunn, (1993 Oct 21; 1994 Apr 22; Stu Dybek, (1993 Aug 15, Sep 12, Nov 30); Stanley Elkin, (1993 Feb 2); Richard Elman, (1992 Feb 25, Jul 13; Apr 26, Jun 12, Jul 25, Aug 7, 16, Dec 3; 1994 Mar 16); Louisa Enright, (1993 May 7); Barbara Esstman, (1992 Jan 11); David Fine, (1992 Sep 11, Nov 6; 1993 Jan 25, Feb 13, Mar 16, Jun 30; 1994 Apr 8); F. Scott Fitzgerald, critical essays re (1990 Dec 7; 1993 Sep 20); Lynn Freed, (1993 Jan 19, Feb 10); Laura Furman, (1992 Aug 17; 1993 Jul 12); George Garrett, (1992 May 15); Reginald Gibbons, (1992 May 14); M. Smith Gibbs, (1992 Aug 9, Jul 16; 1994 Mar 4); Molly Giles, (1992 May 15); Douglas Glover, (1992 Sep 18; 1993 Mar 3); Herbert Gold, (1994 Mar 28); Laurence Goldstein, (1993 Jun 18; 1994 May 2); Stephanie Gunning, (1993 Jul 9; 1994 Jan 28, Feb 17); Sunita Gurung, (1992 Dec 6); Al Haley, (1993 Jan 12); Barry Hannah, (1993 Jun 8); Reginald Hill, (1994 Feb 2); Rick Hillis, (1992 Dec 14); Edward Hirsch, (1992 Jun 16, Oct 22); Jane Hirshfield, (1993 Sep 24); Edward Hoagland, (1992 Nov 16); Jim and Jeanne Houston, (1992 Sep 18, Oct 6, 13, Dec 30; 1993 Dec 6; 1994 Jan 28, Feb 28, Mar 30); Josephine Humphreys, (1992 Jun 14; 1994 Jan 1, 27, n.d.); Sonja James, (1993 Jul 19); Japan (1993 Dec 13); Fenton Johnson, (1993 May 1); Greg Johnson, (1992 Sep 5, Dec 21; 1993 Jan 18, Apr 21); David Michael Kaplan, (1992 Sep 25, Oct 4); D. Michael Kasum, (1993 May 14); Mary E Kollar,. (1992 May 19, Jul 18, Oct 3, Dec 21); James Howard Kunstler, (1993 Mar 2, 30); Vachel Lindsay, death of (1994 Feb 1); Mary Lockwood, (1992 Oct 22, Dec 7); Barry Lopez, (1993 Aug 9, Sep 17; 1994 May 15); Bret Lott, (1992 Oct 15; 1994 Jan 4); Dianne Luce, (1992 Feb 13); Daryl McGrath, (1992 Jul 22, Sep 21; 1993 Jan 20, Jul 19, Aug 10; 1994 Feb 20); Victoria McKernan, (1992 Jul 8); John MacLean, (1992 May 12); Terry McMillan, (1993 Jan 4); Maureen McSherry, (1993 Aug 31); David Madden, (1992 Sep 26, Nov 7); Norman Mailer, (1993 Jul 7); Malamud Committee (1993 Apr 23); Mary Malone, (1993 Aug 12); Manly, Inc. (1988 Dec 2, Sep 23); Mitch Markowitz, (1993 May 10, Dec 5; 1994 Feb 18, Mar 11, Apr 28); Caroline Marshall, (1993 Apr 27, Aug 2; 1994 Mar 30); Tana Maurer, (1993 Mar 15, Apr 7); Barbara Methuin, (1992 Apr 12); Arabella Meyer, (1993 Jun 1, Jul 8, Nov 19); Elizabeth Seydel Morgan, (1992 Oct 31); Micah Morrison, (1993 May 18, Dec 29); Faye Moskowitz, (1993 Nov 12); Craig Nova, (1992 Aug 31); Debra Nystrom, (1992 Sep 29); Flo Oates, (1992 Dec 8); Roy Olson, (1993 May 21, Jun 7); Charlotte Painter, (1992 Oct 28; 1994 Jan 14); Rachel Pastan, (1993 Feb 5); Richard Peabody, (1992 Jul 2, 24, Dec 7); Allen Peacock, (1992 Oct 15); Tito Perdue, (1993 Apr 24); Constance Pierce, (1992 Sep 3, 9, Oct 21); Robert Phillips, (1993 Jan 27, Feb 8, Apr 19, Jun 16); Rebekah Presson, (1992 Aug 5, Sep 14, 27); Lawrence Raab, (1993 Mar 31); Bin Ramke, (1992 Dec 18); Elizabeth Rees, (1989 Mar 11); Roxana Robinson, (1993 Jan 18); Javier Rodriguez, (1993 Apr 13); Lois Rosenthal, (1994 Feb 1); Jim Salter, (1993 Oct 24; 1994 Apr 26; n.d.); Scott Russell Sanders, (1992 Dec 3, 28); Stephen Sandy, (1992 Jul 17, Sep 19, 26; 1993 Jan 7, Dec 3, 24, 30; 1994 Jan 29, Feb 14, Mar 14); Jill Schulz, (1992 May 29); Robbie Shapard, (1992 Nov 18); Marc J Sheehan,. (1992 Nov 17); Barry Silesky, (1993 Apr 9, Aug 20; n.d.); Slovakia (1993 Nov 16); Marc Smirnoff, (1992 Nov 27); Lee Smith, (1993 Dec 9; 1994 Feb 23); Tricia Snell, (1991 Oct 15; 1992 Aug 31, Dec 16, 22); Sobel Weber Associates (1988 Nov 28, Dec 1; 1990 Mar 30; 1992 Jul 1, 12, 15, Dec 10, 11; 1993 Apr 8, 25, Oct 21); Les Staniford, (1993 Sep 29; 1994 Feb 23); Domenic Stansberry, (1993 Jul 22); Marion and Wallace Stegner, (1992 Oct 31, Dec 31; 1993 Feb 22, Oct 1; 1994 Apr 15, May 20); Daniel Stern, (1993 Feb 5); Nan Talese, (1993 Feb 1, May 4); Jack Taub, (1992 Jul 7); Philip Taylor, (1993 May 3); Paul Theroux, (1992 Nov 15); Joyce Carol Thomas, (1992 Nov 16); Judy Troy, (1993 Jun 21, 28); Kathleen Tyau, (1993 Aug 30, Jul 20; 1994 Apr 26); John Updike, (1993 Aug 31); Jon Manchip White, (1993 Sep 6, Nov 23; 1994 Jan 10, Mar 2, Jun 8); Liza Wieland, (1992 May 15); Allen Wier, (1993 Nov 16); C.K. Williams, (1994 Apr 20); George Witte, (1992 May 8); Al Young, (1992 Jul 20, Oct 2); Kit Young, (1993 Jul 2); Zephyr Press (1993 Dec 17)
Correspondents in the Sound of Writing Correspondence (Box 4) include: Lee Smith, Joyce Carol Oates, Wright Morris, Francois Comoin, David Madden, Madison Bell, Tom Boyle, Bob Shacochis, Roy Blount, Jr., Lore Segal, Laura Furman, Fred Chappell, Richard Elman, Jay Neugeboren, Susan Hannah, Lewis Nordan, Monroe Engel, Amy Hempel, Fred Busch, McDonald Harris, Rita Dove, Ursula K. LeGuin, Stuart Dybek, Charlie Baxter, Ann Beattie, Robert Dunn, John Updike, Ray Bradbury, Laura Hendrie, Tobias Wolff, David Michael Kaplan, Gina Berriault, Edward Hoagland, Nicholas Delbanco, Al Young, and Bill Kittredge.
Contents List
- MANUSCRIPTS BY ALAN CHEUSE and OTHERS
  - "An Afternoon of Harp Music in Lake Charles, Louisiana," by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., 4 TMs (Box 1)
  - Articles about Alan Cheuse, Norman Mailer, and Richard Wright 1992-1993, TMs and Print (Box 1)
  - Articles by Other Writers, including Mark Edmundson, George Garrett, Molly Giles, James D. Houston, Jay Parini, and Marjorie Pryse 1991-1992, n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Double Wonder: The Novelistic Achievement of James Houston" by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., 3 TMs (Box 1)
  - "Fitzgerald's Christmas Carol, or The Burden of 'The Camel's Back'" by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
  - The Grandmothers' Club"Author's Note" by Alan Cheuse and "Afterword" by John W. Aldridge for a Paperback Edition, Southern Methodist University Press 1994, 3 TMs (Box 1)
  - William Kennedy Introduction at the Folger Shakespeare Library by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections 1993 Mar 12, TMs (Box 1)
  - Listening to Ourselves edited by Alan Cheuse and Caroline Marshall (2 folders) 1993, galleys (EC) (Box 1)
  - Listening to Ourselves"Introduction" by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections 1993, TMs (Box 1)
  - "Midnight Ride" by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., 3 TMs (Box 1)
  - Rabbi Guatemala A Suite of Scenes by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., TMs (Box 1)
  - Reviews of Books by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections (2 folders) ca. 1991-1994, TMs and print (Box 2)
  - Reviews by Alan Cheuse for Cable Programming, Channels 16 and 41 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - "Reviews on Tape" in Forbes Magazine Supplement FYIca. 1992-1993, TMs and print (Box 2)
  - Rich in Love- A Screenplay by Alfred Uhry based on the novel by Josephine Humphries 1991, TMs (EC) (Box 2)
  - "Rudolfo Anaya" Pen Faulkner Award Introduction by Alan Cheuse 1994 Apr 29, TMs (Box 2)
  - Short Stories and Poetry by Other Writers, including Lee K. Abbott, Richard Bausch, Jamy Bond, Josephine Carson, Jan Cherubin, Evan S. Connell, Nicholas Delbanco, Robert Drake, Stuart Dybek, Tess Gallagher, Molly Giles, Ethan J. Hauser, Jeanne W. Houston, W.P. Kinsella, Mary Kollar, Mary Lockwood, and Jon Manchip White (2 folders) 1992-1993, n.d., TMs (Box 2)
  - "The Situation of Reviewing" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 2)
  - "A Washington Year" - Journal kept by Alan Cheuse 1992-1993, TMs (Box 2)
  - "Writing It Down For James: Some Thoughts on Reading Toward the Millenium" by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections n.d., 3 TMs (Box 2)
  - "The Year in Literature: USA" in The Encyclopedia Britannica by Alan Cheuse, with autograph corrections 1992-1993, TMs and Print (Box 2)
- TOPICAL and MISCELLANEOUS FILES
  - Appointment Calendars 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Conferences, Panels, and Workshops 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Contracts and Agreements 1986-1994 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1986-1993 (Box 3)
  - Neustadt International Prize for Literature 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Notebook of Story Ideas ca. 1985 (Box 3)
  - Pegasus Prize for Literature 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Printed Material (2 folders) 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Reviews of Listening to Ourselves edited by Alan Cheuse and Caroline Marshall 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Reviews of The Tennessee Waltz by Alan Cheuse, and related material 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - The Sound of Writing Stories: Authors (2 folders) 1992, n.d. (Box 4)
  - The Sound of Writing Stories: Correspondence (2 folders) 1988, n.d. (Box 4)
  - The Sound of Writing Stories: Production Schedules and Write-ups - Scripts (2 folders) ca. 1991-1994 (Box 4)
  - The Sound of Writing Stories: Miscellaneous 1991, n.d. (Box 4)
- CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence (3 folders) 1988-1992 Jul (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (10 folders) 1992 Aug-1993 Jun (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (10 folders) 1993 Jul-1994 Jun, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Promotional Poster for Grove Press designed by Drew Friedman and K. Bidus n.d. (Box 6)
  - WMU-TV Interview of Alan Cheuse, Marquette, Michigan (VC - 40) 1992 Jun 18 (Box 6)
  - Alan Cheuse reading from Fall Out of Heaven on "New Letters on the Air," with an introduction by Rebekah Presson (T-1046) 1987 Oct (Box 6)
  - Alan Cheuse reading from Fall Out of Heaven on "Good Evening" for eleven minutes, "Stowell Story" (T-1047) 1987 Nov 7 (Box 6)
  - Tom Smith of the Writer's Institute at the State University of New York, Albany, interviews Alan Cheuse who discusses Fall Out of Heaven on Public Radio Book Show #3, "The Public Book Show" WAMU, Albany, New York (T-1048) 1988 Jul (Box 6)
  - Author's Panel, consisting of Wakefield, Bernays, Tilghman, Phillips, and Cheuse, discussing modern literature at the New England Booksellers Conference and Exposition, Boston World Trade Center, 2 cassettes (T-1049, T-1050) 1991 Sep 27 (Box 6)
  - Alan Cheuse reading from The Light Possessed at the Modern Languages Auditorium, University of Arizona (T-1051) 1991 Oct 30 (Box 6)
  - George Garrett reading excerpts from his novel in progress The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You at the 2nd Street Gallery (Side A) and George Garrett reading from Whistling In the Dark at Randolph-Macon College with an introduction by Megan Gehman (Side B), (T-1052) n.d. (Box 6)
  - The Sound of Writing Program # 78 featuring "Mortals" and "Peculiar" (T-1053) n.d. (Box 6)